翻译：somehacker  彼岸荼蘼
校对：somehacker
特效：somehacker
万物理论
1963年  英格兰  剑桥
快点
Well, come on!
快点  老头子
Come on, old man.
再不快点就晚了
I think we're going to be late!
我全速前进呢  布莱恩
Fire's on the rocket, Brian.
布莱恩找到了空隙
Brian finds an opening!
别搞砸了
Oy, don't mess up!
霍金的最后冲刺
Hawking's last minute!
谢了  布莱恩
Thanks, Brian!
太慢了  老头子
Too slow, old man.
太慢了
Too slow.
我第一个喝到酒  你好啊
First to find a drink, yeah. Hello.
要是宇宙的奥秘跟性有关
What if the secret of the universe has something to do with sex.
你博士论文就写这个吧  爱之物理学
Maybe do your doctorate on that? The physics of love.
-那是你的研究领域吧  -最近没怎么研究了
- I think that's more your field, Brian. - Not lately.
你要是再定不下来  就要被请出去了
They will boot you out, you know, if you don't decide.
我认识这里所有的...棒极了
I know everybody here who's... brilliant.
居然是科学家们
Oh, dear, scientists!
别担心  不会待太久的
Don't worry, we don't have to stay long...
简直无聊到死
looks mortifyingly dull.
-没劲  -那是谁
- Bores. - Who's that?
哪个  他吗
Who's who? Oh, him?
他可怪了  不过他也去了抗议核游行[1960年代]
He's strange. However, he goes to ban the bomb marches.
Y  缩写是GY
Y... G.Y.
大卫在那  大卫
Oh, there's David... David?
戴安娜
Diana?
-你好  -你好
- Hello. - Hello.
-理学吗  -文学
- Science? - Arts.
-英语  -法语及西班牙语
- English. - French and Spanish.
那你呢  你学什么的
What about you? What are you?
-宇宙学家  我是个宇宙学家  -那是什么
- Cosmologist, I'm a cosmologist. - What's that?
就是特别聪明的  不信上帝的人
It's a kind of religion for
-信的宗教  -聪明的不信上帝的
- intelligent atheists. - Intelligent atheists?
你不信教吧
You're not religious, are you?
国教
C. Of E.
-就是英国国教[圣公会]  -是啊
- Church of England. - England, yes.
总得有个信教的
I suppose someone has to be.
那宇宙学家信奉什么呢
So, what do cosmologists worship then?
信奉什么
What do we worship?
用一个统一的方程
One single unifying equation
来解释宇宙万物
that explains everything in the universe.
-是吗  -是
- Really. - Yes.
是什么方程
What's the equation?
问题就在这
That is the question.
这个问题非常好  我还没想出来
And a very good question. I'm not quite sure yet.
但我想研究这个
But I intend to find out.
那你为什么去牛津啊
Then why do you even stay at Oxford?
因为我的期末考试
Because my finals exams are such a
考得一塌糊涂  他们叫我参加个口试
shambles that the examiners they settled me in for a "Viva",
-他们如果我拿到二等  -口试是什么
- And they told me that if I go up a second... - What's a "Viva"?
有点恐怖  跟人面对面坐下来什么的
A sort of, mildly terrifying face-to-face thingy.
-面试吗  -审讯吧
- As an interview? - An interrogation.
我告诉他们  如果给我二等学位[参考片尾注释]
And I told them that if they gave me a 2nd class degree
我就得留在牛津做研究
then I'd stay with them and do my research at Oxford,
如果给我一等学位  我就能去剑桥了
but if they gave me the 1st, I needed to get into Cambridge, then
他们就能永远甩掉我了
they would never have to see me again.
-所以他们给了你一等  -没错
- They gave you the 1st. - They gave me the 1st.
-是啊  -派对已经正式结束了
- Of course. - This party is officially deceased.
来吧  我找辆车送你回家
Come on, I've fixed you up a ride home.
走啊  简  简
Come on, Jane... Jane?
-跟你聊天很开心  -我也是
- Well, it was lovely to talk to you. - Yes.
还有  希望你能找到那个方程
And... I hope you find your equation.
是啊
Yes... oh...
-再见  -再见
- Bye. - G'bye.
斯蒂芬
Stephen?
很好
Good.
来看看这个
Well, then, here we are,
给你们的小测试
a little challenge for you all,
在你们的学术研究路上...
as you embark upon your separate doctoral journeys...
不管你们打算研究什么  霍金先生
whatever they may be, Mr. Hawking.
传下去
Pass them down.
来看看你们是男人还是男孩
Something to separate the men from the boys,
是粮食还是糟糠
the wheat from the chaff,
介子还是π介子  真夸克[基本粒子之一]还是假行家
the mesons from the pi-mesons, the quarks from the quacks.
十个问题  一个比一个难
Ten questions, each more impregnable than the last.
祝你们好运吧  周五三点再见
Good luck, you'll need it. Shall we say Friday at 3 o'clock?
我要做到瘫痪了
This is going to hospitalize me.
好了  划  划  划  划
All right! Row! Row! Row! Row!
使劲划  布莱恩  加油啊
Row it out, Brian! Come on, Brian!
划  布莱恩  加油
Row, Brian! Come on! Row, Brian.
向前进  布莱恩
Straight on, Brian!
再来两杯这个
Can I get two more of those, please?
-换点零钱打个电话  -好的
- And some change for phone, Sir. - Yeah.
-不拿走吗  -简
- Take her out, man. - Jane.
猜我那天碰到谁了  卡罗琳
You'll never guess who I saw the other day... Caroline.
她好像有男朋友了  不过她爱约谁约谁
I think she was having a date, she can have him, quite frankly.
这概率有多大
What's the probability?
小的不得了
Reasonably low.
这个  这是斯蒂芬
Uh... this is... this is Stephen.
-你玩槌球吗  -槌球
- Do you play croquet? - Croquet?
-有阵子没玩了  -周日早上
- Not recently. - Sunday morning.
我周日早上有事
I'm actually busy on Sunday mornings.
是啊  跟上帝[做礼拜]
Oh... Him.
好吧
Okay.
快起床  你做出了几个
Oh, come on, get up! How many did you get?
-早上好  布莱恩  -下午好  斯蒂芬
- Morning, Brian. - Good afternoon, Stephen.
那几个问题你做出几个
How many of the possible questions did you do?
布莱恩  你在说什么啊
Brian, I have no idea what you're talking about.
夏玛的问题  你做出几个  斯蒂芬
How many of Sciama's questions did you get, Stephen?
-没做  -一个没做吗
- None. - You didn't get any?
我一会再做
I was going to do them later.
你看都没看
You haven't even looked at them.
没看
No.
斯蒂芬  你知道自己
Stephen, are you aware that
是自愿攻读物理学博士学位的吧
you've voluntarily embarked on a PhD in physics?
还是在英国最顶尖的大学里
At the most prestigious college in England?
知道
Yes.
还以为入学典礼时候你睡着了呢
Oh! Thought maybe you'd slept through the induction or something.
布莱恩
Brian?
-怎么了  -放段瓦格纳吧
- What? - Can you whip on some Wagner?
一边去
Sod off!
-请进  斯蒂芬  -抱歉
- Come in, Stephen. - Sorry.
迈克  你这乱成一坨
Michael, that's so illegible
我也不知道你错了多少  估计是不少
I can't quite decipher how wrong it is, I suspect enormously,
布莱恩  看不懂你写的什么
and Brian... that's just baffling.
-您受累做了没  -抱歉
- Have you even bothered to? - Oh, sorry.
列车时刻表
Train time tables.
这怎么行  这时刻表都过期了
It's certainly unacceptable, these expired a month ago.
在背面  我出了点事
It's on the back, I had a little accident.
只能做出九个
I could only do nine.
好吧  谢天谢地  那个
Well... oh... thank God... however...
九个
Nine?
请进
Come in.
斯蒂芬  坐吧
Oh, Stephen, take a seat.
我想谈谈你的课题
I wanted to talk to you about your subject.
我们都等着你决定研究方向呢
We're all rather concerned as to what it's going to be.
我定不下来
I can't decide.
有什么想法吗
Do you have any ideas?
没有
No.
汤普森在这发现了电子[1897年]
This is where J.J. Thomson discovered the electron,
卢瑟福在这分裂了原子核[1909年]
and where Rutherford split the atom.
在剑桥搞研究的好处就是  你永远都不知道
You know, one of the great rewards of this job is one never knows
谁  在哪里
from where the next great
能搞出个重大发现来
leap forward is going to come, or from whom.
下周五  我要带几个优秀研究生去伦敦
Next Friday, I'm taking a few graduates of merit to London,
参加数学家罗杰·彭罗斯的讲座
to attend a talk by the mathematician Roger Penrose.
你也来吧  如果有兴趣的话
You come along... if you're interested.
走的时候记得关门
Oh, and close the door as you leave.
听说你从没去过教堂
So, I gather you've never been to church?
-很久以前去过  -想信教吗
- Once upon a time. - Tempted to convert?
我不太信这种统领万物的神
I have a slight problem with the whole Celestial Dictator premise.
你午饭有安排吗  我妈烤的肉特别好吃
Now, what are you doing for lunch? Ma makes a cracking roast.
简  你是学什么的
So, Jane, what are you studying?
-文学  -要球甘蓝吗
- Arts. - Sprouts?
谢谢
Thank you.
法语和西班牙语  毕业希望继续读博
French and Spanish, and hoping to do a PhD eventually.
哪个方向呢
Oh, one arm.
中世纪伊波利亚半岛诗歌
Medieval poetry of the Iberian Peninsula.
中世纪诗歌...你喜欢哪位画家
Medieval poets... What painters do you like?
-我喜欢特纳  -特纳吗
- Well, I like Turner. - Turner, really?
我一直觉得他的画
You know, I always feel that his
像是被暴雨泡了好几天
paintings look as if they've been left out in the rain.
还有  威廉·布雷克
And... William Blake.
-简  来尝尝我的接骨木酒  -谢谢
- Jane, have some of my elderflower wine. - Yes, yes, thank you.
别试  别试  简
Don't touch it, don't touch it, Jane.
谢谢  他妈呢
Thank you. Mother.
斯蒂芬不喜欢我自己酿的酒  菲丽西汀呢
Stephen doesn't like my homemade wine...Philistine.
给你塞几瓶带回学校
I'm going to send you back with a couple of bottles.
斯蒂芬  你和这位善良的女士去了教堂
So, Stephen, you have come to church with a good woman.
觉得自己圣洁吗
Are you feeling holier than thou?
非常圣洁  谢谢
Positively saintly... thank you.
你还没说自己为什么不信上帝
You haven't said why you don't believe in God.
物理学家的研究
A physicist can't allow his calculations
不能受超自然的创世主影响
to be muddled by a belief in a supernatural creator.
你说得像是在指责物理学家啊
Sounds less of an argument against God than against physicists.
鸡胸还是鸡腿
Light or dark?
-简  鸡胸还是鸡腿  -鸡胸  谢谢
- Jane, light meat or dark? - Light, please.
我要请简做我五月舞会[剑桥传统]的舞伴
I'm inviting Jane to be my partner for the May ball.
真的吗  真棒
Really! Very impressive!
你要跳舞了  斯蒂芬
You'll have to dance, won't you, Stephen?
给女仆让个路  好了
Make way for my mother's maid, here we go.
你好
Hello.
-抱歉  -你没事吧
- Sorry. - Are you okay?
-跳舞吧  -不跳
- Should we dance? - No.
不跳了
No.
我不跳  虽然我很喜欢看别人跳
I don't. It's a phenomenon I'm very happy to observe,
但我自己是不会跳的
but I can't possibly imagine participating.
我也这么想的  谁愿意跳舞啊
I absolutely agree. I mean, who would want to dance?
说真的  我不跳舞
No, I'm serious, I don't dance.
那就不跳了
No dancing then.
你看男生的衬衫前胸
Do you see how the men's shirt-fronts
还有领结  比女生的礼服还闪亮
and their bow ties how they glow more than the womens' dresses?
-是啊  -知道为什么吗
- Yes. - Do you know why?
-为什么  -汰渍
- Why? - Tide.
洗衣粉
Washing powder.
洗衣粉里的荧光物质在紫外线照射下发光
The fluorescence in the washing powder is caught by the UV light.
你怎么知道的
Why do you know that?
恒星诞生和毁灭时  会辐射出紫外线
When stars are born and when they die, they emit UV radiation.
如果只能看到夜空里的紫外线
So, if we could see the night sky in ultraviolet light,
现在的星星就都不见了
then almost all the stars would disappear
只剩下恒星壮丽的诞生和毁灭
and all that we would see are these spectacular births and deaths.
-我觉得应该...  -就像这个
- And I reckon it would look a little... - Like that.
-为什么  -什么为什么
- So, why? - Why what?
为什么要研究中世纪西班牙诗歌
Why Spanish medieval poetry?
应该是我喜欢穿越时空吧...
I suppose I like to time travel...
...像你一样
...like you.
有哪段时空是你特别想去的吗
Are there any particular time periods that you'd like to visit?
-二十年代吧  -咆哮的二十年代吗[1920  北美]
- The imagine it's the Twenties. - The Roaring Twenties?
耶茨  《The Song of the Happy Shepherd》
"不要在天文学家那找寻知识
"Seek, then, No learning from starry men,
"他们只是用望远镜
"Who follow with the optic glass
"追随恒星纷飞的路径"
"The whirling ways of stars that pass."
真棒
Bravo!
"创世之初  只有天地
"In the beginning was the heaven and the earth,
大地混沌  没有定型"
and the earth was without form,"
"黑暗笼罩着深渊"
"And darkness was upon the face of the deep."
和我共舞一曲吧
Would you dance with me?
三号站台  前往伦敦国王十字车站的列车
The train now departing from track number three is
将于九点十五发车
the nine-fifteen service to London King's Cross.
快点  斯蒂芬  快点
Come on, Stephen. Get a move on.
怎么了你  快上来
What's wrong with you, man? Come up top.
一颗恒星  体积是太阳的三倍多
A star, more than three times the size of our sun...
就要走到尽头  怎么结束呢  坍落
ought to end its life, how? With a collapse.
整颗恒星的引力
The gravitational forces of the entire mass overcoming
克服了原子之间的斥力
the electromagnetic forces of individual atoms,
向内坍落
and so collapsing inwards.
如果质量足够大  还会继续坍落
If the star is massive enough, it will continue this collapse,
形成一个黑洞  翘曲了时空
creating a black hole, where the warping of space-time
什么都逃不出去  包括光
is so great that nothing can escape... not even light.
变得越来越小  越小
It gets... smaller... smaller.
恒星的密度越来越大
The star, in fact, gets denser
原子  甚至原子内的粒子都被压缩了
as atoms, even subatomic particles get literally crushed into smaller and smaller space.
那最终  我们得到了什么
And at its end point what are we left with?
时空奇点
A space time singularity.
时空在这里停止
Space and time come to a stop.
我在想  如果把彭罗斯的理论
I wonder what would happen if you applied
从黑洞推广到整个宇宙呢
Penrose's theory about black holes to the entire universe?
如果爱因斯坦是对的
If Einstein is right,
或者说广义相对论是对的  那宇宙是在膨胀的
or if general relativity is correct, then the universe is expanding, yes?
对吧
Yes?
-对  -好了
- Yes. - Okay, so...
如果时光倒流  宇宙就是在缩小
If you reverse time, then the universe is getting smaller.
-没错  -那么
- All right. - So...
如果一路倒退回去
What if I reverse the process all the way
回到时间的起点呢
back to see what happened at the beginning of Time itself?
-时间的起点  -对
- The beginning of Time itself? - Yes.
宇宙越来越小
The universe, getting smaller and smaller,
密度越来越大  温度越来越高
getting denser and denser, hotter and hotter as...
随着时间的倒流
As you wind back the clock.
-没错  时光倒流  -时光倒流
- Exactly, you wind back the clock. - Wind back the clock.
你是想让时光倒流吗[逆时针]
Is that what you're doing? You're winding back the clock.
没错
Exactly what I'm doing.
继续转  还有好久呢  继续转
Well, keep winding! You've got quite a way to go! Keep winding.
我怕摔倒
I don't want to fall down.
你得回到时间的起点
Well, you've got to go back to the beginning of time.
可有你转的  接着转  别停
You've got a long way to go, so, keep winding, keep winding!
直到...
Until you get...
奇点
A singularity.
时空奇点
A space-time singularity,
宇宙源自黑洞的爆炸
so the universe born from a black hole exploding.
-继续  -继续什么
- Keep going. - What do you mean, "Keep going", what...
宇宙起源之前吗
before the universe began?
不是  继续  用数学来解决
No, no, no, no! Keep going, develop the mathematics!
用力顶  用力顶
Push it as hard as you can! Push it, push it!
-用力  -我用力了
- As hard as you can. - I am pushing as hard as I can.
怎么...  一  二  一  二
What... I count 1... 1, 2... 1, 2...
好了
All right, all right.
无名指  第四个夹子
Fourth finger, fourth peg.
是运动神经元病
It's called motor neuron disease.
神经元逐步失调
It's a progressive neurological disorder
导致控制肌肉运动的脑细胞受损
that destroys the cells in the brain that control essential muscle activity,
比如
such as...
讲话  行走  呼吸  吞咽
Speaking, walking, breathing, swallowing
控制肌肉运动的电信号收到了干扰
The signals that muscles must receive in order to move are disrupted.
结果就是肌肉逐步萎缩
The result is... gradual muscle decay, wasting away.
最终  丧失
Eventually, the ability to
运动能力  彻底地
control voluntary movement is... lost... entirely.
平均寿命是发病后两年
I'm afraid average life expectancy is two years.
我也无能为力
There's nothing I can do for you.
大脑呢
What about the brain?
大脑不受影响  你的思想依然在
The brain isn't affected, you're thoughts won't change.
就是
It's... just that...
到最后  没人能知道你在想什么了
Well, eventually, no one will know what they are.
非常抱歉
I'm ever so sorry.
欢迎收看本周的自然世界
Well, welcome to this week's episode of "The Natural World",
这次  我们将一起探索剑桥一位杰出物理学家
where this week we explore the bizarre hibernation patterns
他的冬眠规律
of the rare Cambridge Physicist,
就是盛装的这位
seen here in his remarkable plumage..."
怎么样  他们怎么说的  你的手腕怎么样
So, how was it? What did they say, how's your wrist?
我病了  布莱恩
I have a disease, Bri.
是花柳病吗  斯蒂芬
Is it venereal... Stephen?
是运动神经元病
I have motor neuron disease.
不好意思
Sorry, I don't...
卢·葛雷克病  他是个棒球运动员
It's Lou Gehrig's disease, he's a baseball player.
不好意思  神经运动  棒球什么的病
Sorry, I'm lagging behind in my pioneering research into
我还没深入研究过
skilled motor, baseball related diseases.
-我还剩两年  -什么
- I have two years to live. - Sorry?
大声说出来就不那么怪了是吧
It does sound odd when you say it out loud, doesn't it?
什么意思  你干什么
Whatchya mean? What are you doing?
他们  他们
What did... what did... what...
他们怎么说的  我刚没仔细...
what did they say? Sorry, I... I don't really...
走吧  布莱恩
Will you go, Brian?
斯蒂芬  是我太蠢了
Stephen, I was just being a berk...
我没...我肯定...
I didn't... I'm so... I'll be...
走吧
You go.
斯蒂芬  找你的电话  是个姑娘
Stephen, phone for you. It's a girl.
-回头见  好的
- I'll see you soon. - Yes.
她在等着呢
She's waiting.
斯蒂芬
Stephen?
-简  -布莱恩
- Jane! - Brian.
真抱歉  我
I'm sorry... I'm...
你坐下吧
Why don't you sit down.
真抱歉  是斯蒂芬的事
I'm so sorry. It's about Stephen.
他之前住院...
You know he was in hospital...
有教育意义吗
Something educational?
非常有
Very.
约翰跟玛莎有外遇
John is having an affair with Martha,
可玛莎爱着阿兰
but Martha is in love with Alan,
不过阿兰应该是同性恋
and I think that Alan is probably homosexual,
看他的毛衣  我呢  我在尽力
by the look of his jumper, so, well, I'm just trying
计算他们幸福的可能性
to work out the mathematical probability of happiness.
要算出来了吗
Are you close?
应该是零点几  不过还差着远呢
It's some integer of zero, but, no, I'm not quite there yet.
-斯蒂芬  -他刚走
- Stephen. - You just missed him.
之前还在这
He was here earlier.
别这样
Don't do this.
走吧
Go!
好吧
Okay.
跟我玩个游戏
Play a game with me.
快走
Go!
你要是不站起来跟我打一场
If you don't get up and play a game with me...
我就不回来了
I won't come back here again...
永远不来了
...ever.
来吧
Come on!
你走吧
You can leave me now.
你不想谈谈吗
Are you going to talk about this or not?
-快走不好吗  -你想要我走吗
- Will you please just go? - Is that what you want?
是  我想要你走  走吧
Yes, it is what I want, so, please,
你要是还在乎我  就走吧
if you care about me all, then, please, just go!
-不行  -我只剩两年了
- I can't. - I have two years to live.
-我还要工作  -我爱你
- I need to work. - I love you.
你这  你得出了错误结论
You've... you've leapt to... that's a false conclusion...
我要和你在一起  有多就是多久
I want us to be together, for as long as we've got,
时间不长的话
and if that's not very long then, well,
也没事  两年也够
that's just how it is... it'll have to do.
你不知道会怎么样  我的一切都受影响
You don't know what's coming. It'll affect everything.
你眼镜总是这么脏
Your glasses are always dirty.
给你
There.
好多了吧
That's better, isn't it?
嗯
Yes.
是啊
Yes, it is.
...在盒子边缘
...the solutions to the Schrodinger
薛定谔方程是无解的  所以...
equation must vanish at the boundary of the box, so we have...
时间
Time!
你的课题是时间吗
Time, that's your subject?
有具体方向吗
Any aspect in particular?
就是时间
Time.
请进  请进
Come in, come in.
你应该不知道自己面对的是什么  简
I don't think you realize what lies ahead, Jane.
他的寿命非常短
His life is going to be very short.
要小心  你是在和科学作对
So, be careful, the weight of science is against you.
而且你没有抗争的机会
And this will not be a fight, Jane.
我们都会被打败
This is going to be a very heavy defeat...
...所有人
...for all of us.
我知道你们都怎么想
I know what you all think... that...
觉得我不是很坚强
That I don't look a terribly strong person.
可我爱他
But I love him.
他也爱我
And he loves me.
我们要一起抗争...
We're going to fight this illness together...
...大家一起
...all of us.
祝你好运
Good luck.
-早上好  斯蒂芬  -早上好  雷夫
- Good morning, Stephen. - Good morning, Rev.
我知道  我知道
I know, I know...
-...方程要更优雅一点  -是啊
- ...got to be a little more elegant. - Yes, that's what...
我懂...
I understand...
进来吧  斯蒂芬
Come in, Stephen.
我知道  一开始都担心这个
I know it's something we're all worried about initially.
你保留了些意见...
You had some reservations about it...
等着瞧吧
Well, well, we'll see.
-欢迎  斯蒂芬  -早上好
- Welcome, Stephen. - Morning.
-请坐吧  -不用  谢谢
- Would you like to take a seat? - No, I'm fine, thank you.
确定吗
You're sure?
好吧  总体来说
So, so you... in summary.
第一章  漏洞百出
As we know, chapter one, full of holes.
缺乏数理支持
Lacks mathematical support.
-基普·索恩教授  -第二章  原创的
- Professor Thorne. - Chapter Two, now, really original.
用了不少罗杰的观点
Uses a lot of Roger's ideas.
至少你还支持我的观点
Well, at least you run with them.
第三章  留了太多疑问
Chapter three, too many unanswered questions.
没错
I agree.
当然了  还有第四章
And then, of course, we have chapter four,
时间起点的黑洞
this black hole at the beginning of time.
-时空奇点  -没错
- Space-time singularity? - Indeed.
太棒了
It's brilliant!
Brilliant.
棒极了
Superb!
那么只剩下一句话了  做得不错
And therefore, all that remains to be said is: Well done!
或者准确点说
Or perhaps, I should say, to be more precise:
-做的不错  博士  -漂亮  斯蒂芬
- Well done, Doctor! - Bravo, Stephen.
这理论真不错
An extraordinary theory.
谢谢
Thank you.
-然后呢  -证明它
- So what next? - Prove it.
用一个方程证明  时间是有起点的
To prove, with a single equation, that time had a beginning.
是不是很棒  教授
Wouldn't that be nice, Professor?
一个简单  优美的方程
With one simple elegant equation
来解释万物
to explain everything?
是啊  肯定很棒
Yes, it would. It would indeed.
受人尊敬的  能力超群的
The esteemed, and formidable...
-博士  -谁[神秘博士]
- Doctor. - Who?
斯蒂芬·霍金博士
Doctor Stephen Hawking.
敬斯蒂芬·霍金
To Stephen Hawking.
谢谢  简
Thank you, Jane.
真神奇  他是第一个担心自己努力不够
It is astonishing that he's the first person
还能拿到博士学位的人
to receive his doctorate fearing what little work he's be doing.
努力是霍金最讨厌的词
"Work" Was the worst four-letter word for Stephen.
甚至在牛津
Even at Oxford,
他平均每天只学习一个小时  一个小时
especially, he averaged an hour, an HOUR a day he averaged.
-就这样  斯蒂芬就是...  -真是神奇  我一开始...
- And that it is. It's Stephen... - It's astonishing that...
过去六个月
And how many of your
我帮你们回了多少信
letters have I covered in the last six months?
你们外出搞研究时候
When you've been doing research trips...
-多少  -四封
- How many? - Four.
-没事吧  -没事  我没事
- Everything all right? - I'm good... I'm fine.
你好啊  罗宾
Hi, Robin.
我没事
It's ok. I'm all right.
真...是...
This...is...
告诉布莱恩
Tell Brian.
好啊
Of course.
方便吃早饭了
Well, it's convenient for breakfast!
谢谢
Thank you.
你刚说什么了
Sorry, did you say something?
我说...
I said...
什么
Yes?
谢谢
Thank you.
看看你
Look at you!
去吧  简
Go, Jane.
马上回来
I'll be one second.
露丝  宝贝
Luce, Baby.
简
Jane.
斯蒂芬
Stephen.
亲爱的
Dear?
我有了个想法
I've got an idea.
我说我有了个想法
I said I've had an idea.
-你好  -你好  丹尼斯
- Hello. - Hi, Dennis.
-你好  丹尼斯  -你好
- Hello, Dennis. - Hi.
好了  我爱你
Okay, I love you.
他没事的  他没事的
He'll be fine, he'll be fine.
-抱歉  没关系
- Sorry. - No problem.
...我们可以推断
...allowing us to predict that
有些粒子  是可以逃离黑洞的
some particles can in fact escape a black hole.
黑洞  并不是那么黑的
The black holes are not, in fact, black at all,
它散发着热辐射
but glow with heat radiation.
...也就是说
...the steady emission of
黑洞在稳定地辐射热能  损失质量
heat energy causes the black holes to lose mass,
最终以爆炸的方式消失
and eventually they disappear in a spectacular explosion.
非常  非常简单  物体散发热量
It's very, very simple, when a hot body loses heat...
热力学第二定理
Second law of thermodynamics.
-没错  热力学  -就在...
- He's right, it's thermodynamics. - In... in...
想象一下  如果的确
If we can imagine that the black hole is, indeed,
有粒子不断逃离黑洞
losing particles, then,
那假以时日  黑洞的体积就会减小  会蒸发
over time it will diminish in size, it will evaporate.
-然后  -消失
- It will... - Disappear.
所以
So...
首先  恒星消失  坍落成黑洞
First a star vanishes into a black hole,
然后  黑洞也要...
but then the black hole itself must...
消失  虚无
Gone! Nothing!
-从虚无到虚无  -你欠我杯啤酒
- From nothing to nothing. - You owe me another beer.
我得告诉你
I have to show you that our
我们的朋友证明了时间是有起点的
friend has proven that time, indeed has a beginning.
不仅是这个  还有宇宙如何出现  如何消亡
Not only that, how the universe was born, and how it will end.
-砰  -咔嚓
- Bang! - Crunch!
多美  多生动
It's beautiful! It's racy!
真荒唐  胡言乱语
Complete nonsense. It's preposterous.
是因为我说的东西吗  教授
Was it something I said, Professor?
抱歉
Excuse me.
我叫
My name...
我是卡拉提诺夫教授
My name is Professor Khalatnikov.
来自苏维埃理工学院
from Soviet Academy of Sciences.
我的研究领域  是热宇宙的演化
As you know, my field is evolution of the hot universe,
宇宙微波背景辐射的性质
the properties of the microwave background radiation,
还有黑洞理论
and theory of the black holes.
说实话...
To be honest...
我今天来...
I came here today...
...就是想听胡言乱语的
...expecting to hear a lot of nonsense.
然后失望地回家
I go home disappointed.
这位小伙子做到了
The little one here... has done it.
他做到了
He has done it!
见到你真荣幸
It has been a pleasure to meet you,
-教授  -彼此彼此
- Professor. - Likewise, likewise.
-还算顺利嘛  -是挺顺利的
- That went pretty well. - It's probably for awhile.
霍金辐射  这位小伙子做到了
Hawking radiation! The little one has done it!
这位小伙子做到了
The little one has done it!
-快点  天才  -真好笑
- Come on, Genius! - Oh, very funny!
就推你到这了  老头子
You've had enough of that, Old Man.
用力  小子  1  2  3
Come on, codger. 1, 2, 3...
天哪  简是怎么做到的
God! How does Jane manage?
斯蒂芬  你那个运动口腔什么的病  会不会影响...
Stephen, your Motor "Mouth" Disease, does it effect...
什么
What?
一切
Everything?
另一套系统  自动的
Different system... automatic.
真的吗
You serious?
那还算不错嘛
Well, that's a bit wonderful, isn't it?
对男人的理解又进了一步
Well, it certainly explains a lot about men.
快点
Hurry up! Come on!
霍金辐射
-里面有什么  -惊喜
- What's in there? - It's a surprise!
别睁开
Keep them closed.
爸爸  快看
Look, Daddy, look!
这是电动轮椅
That is an electric wheelchair.
不喜欢的话可以退回去
If you don't like it, we can take it back.
我不明白...
I don't understand...
你花了好多年假设黑洞存在
you've spent years assuming black holes exist, and
你相信天鹅座X-1星很可能
you believe Cygnus X-1 could well turn out to be
是我们能观测到的第一个黑洞
the first black hole that we can actually observe,
却还跟基普·索恩赌它不是
and yet you bet Kip Thorne it's not a black hole?
-是的  -赌什么
- Yes. - What did you bet him?
赌一年的杂志
A one year's subscription to a magazine.
-什么杂志  《自然》吗  -不是  《阁楼》
- Which magazine? Nature? - No! Penthouse!
-《阁楼》吗  -没错
- Penthouse? - Yes.
抓到你了
Gonna get you!
爸爸  快点  得快点
Daddy! Come up! You need to hurry!
妈妈  妈妈  快来看
Mummy! Muumy! Come and look!
抓到你了
I'm gonna get you!
一整天  一整天  一整天  一整天
All that day! All that day! All that day! All that day!
-你好  -你好
- Hello! - Hello!
-你好  -来了啊
- Hello! - There you are!
你好  布什
Hello, Bush.
这该死的台阶  弗兰克
The bloody steps, Frank.
-简  斯蒂芬  -你好
- Jane, Stephen! - Hello.
终于来了
Here we are!
好了
Yes, here we go.
等上去了就方便多了  你好啊  斯蒂芬
And once we're up at the top, it's very snug... hello, Stephen.
好了
Here we go.
-来给你转个身  -要我推一下吗
- We'll turn you around, Stephen. - You want me to push?
不用  我没事  你去拿行李吧
No, no, I'll be fine, you get the luggage.
好了  我来
Here we go, off, we got it.
好了  多简单
There we are, you see. Quite easy.
上了一级
One, there we go.
下雨了  冷得让人发抖
Um... the... rain coming down, shivering, cold, no, uh...
下了  下了
The... falling... falling... um...
-非常冷  -是什么
- Very cold. - What is it?
我...我不太...
I can... I'm having a...
出来了吗
Is it out?
-要点水吗  -不用  没事
- Some... some water? - No, don't worry.
好了  没事了
You're okay. That's it.
没事了  没事了
There we go. It's okay. It's okay.
得去看医生
He needs to see a specialist.
老是这样
It keeps happening over and over again.
-不看医生  不看医生  -好  不看
- No doctors. No doctors! - All right, no doctors.
来点水
A little water.
斯蒂芬
Stephen?
我需要帮手
I need help.
为了罗伯特  他的童年都被我拖累了
If only for Robert, it... he's missing out on his childhood.
我想努力把这个家经营下去
I keep looking for a way to make this work,
可我一个人做不到
but I can't find it on my own.
没问题啊  我们是个正常的家庭
Everything is fine, we're just a normal family.
哪里正常了
We're not a normal family.
We're not a normal family!
罗伯特  你妈妈对我非常生气
Robert, your mother is very angry with me.
谢谢啊
Thanks.
简
Jane?
简  停下
Jane! Stop!
坐下
Sit!
好了...
Now...
我给你提个建议
I'd like to make a suggestion.
听着有点奇怪  可也帮过大忙
It might sound unusual, but I have seen it work wonders.
我觉得你应该加入唱诗班
I think that you should consider joining the church choir.
妈妈
Mum...
我好久都没听过
I think that's possibly
这么贴心的话了
the most English thing anyone has ever said.
也许吧
Maybe so.
-我以前喜欢唱歌  -唱得挺好的
- I used to love singing. - You're very good at it.
-可我也不确定  -去吧
- I don't know about that. - Just go.
每周一小时
It's one hour a week.
真棒  大伙下周见
Really lovely, everyone. Okay, see you next week.
-你好  -你好
- Hello. - Hello.
-是要加入唱诗班吗  -我是来...
- Have you come to sing? - Um... I just came to...
-高音吗  -中音
- Soprano? - Mezzo.
太棒了  正需要中音
Ah! Lovely! Just what we need.
-你早去哪了  -问得好
- Where have you been hiding? - A good question.
反正来得早不如来得巧
Well, you're here now and just in time.
俗话说的
As they say.
-反正我还要回来的  -好
- Ya know, I have to come back anyway. - Great.
-都给你了吗  -是的  谢谢
- Do you have everything? - Yes, thank you, yes.
谢谢你  你肯定是...团里的中流砥柱
Thank you for coming, you will be a... A valuable asset.
谢谢
Thank you.
我  我该走了
Well, I should... I should be going.
要是你儿子想学钢琴...
And... uh... if your son wants those piano lessons, just...
是啊  没问题
Yes, yes, absolutely, I... um...
-肯定找你  -真棒
- I will do. - Great.
我丈夫也喜欢音乐
My... my husband... adores music, too.
他弹什么乐器吗
Oh! Well! Does he play?
我也可以教他的
I could... I could teach him as well.
说来话长  不过...
That's a long story. But, um...
好吧
Ah, okay.
-谢谢你  乔纳森  -不客气  简  再见
- Well, thank you, Jonathan - My pleasure, Jane, see you again.
-再见  -再见
- Bye bye. - Bye bye.
要酒吗
Wine?
好啊  谢谢
Why not, thank you.
-斯蒂芬  -要
- Stephen? - Yes.
斯蒂芬  简跟我说  你有个优美的理论
Stephen, Jane was telling me you have a beautiful theorem...
证明宇宙是有开端的
...that... that proves the universe had a beginning?
我的博士论文
That was my PhD thesis.
我的新课题证明那是错的
My new project disproves it.
是错的
Disproves it?
Yes.
那你不再相信创世理论了
So, then, you no longer believe in the Creation?
在物理学里  人信仰什么是...
What one believes is irrelevant...
...是不重要的
...irrelevant in physics.
好吧
I see.
斯蒂芬来了个大转弯
Stephen's done a U-turn.
新的理论是宇宙没有边界
The big new idea is that the universe has no boundaries at all.
没有边界  没有开端...
No boundaries, no beginning...
...也没有上帝
...and no God. Oh!
明白了  我还以为
Oh, I see... I... I thought that...
你证明宇宙有开端
you'd proved the universe
进一步证明有创世主
had a beginning and thus a need for a Creator.
-我的错  -是我的
- My mistake. - No... mine.
斯蒂芬想找到一个理论
Stephen is looking for a single theory
来解释宇宙中的一切
that explains all the forces in the universe.
这样上帝就必须死
Therefore, God must die.
为什么上帝必须死  我不明白
Why must God die, I don't see.
物理学的两大支柱是  量子论
The two great pillars of physics are: Quantum Theory,
针对所有微小粒子的理论
the laws that govern the very small particles,
电子什么的  还有广义相对论
electrons and so on, and General Relativity.
对  爱因斯坦
Ah, yes, Einstein.
爱因斯坦的理论  针对非常巨大的
Einstein's theory, the law that governs the very large,
恒星什么的  但量子论  和相对论
planets and such, but Quantum, and Relativity...
别说  他们是不一样的
Don't tell me... they're different?
一点也不一样
They don't remotely play by the same rules.
如果宇宙里只有土豆  那很简单
If the world were all potatoes, then, easy
我们可以追溯回去  像斯蒂芬之前一样
you could trace a precise beginning, as Stephen once did,
找到创世的那一刻
a moment of Creation.
哈利路亚  上帝是存在的
Hallelujah, God lives.
可是有了豌豆之后
If you incorporate peas into the menu,
就变得有点...
then it all goes a little...
...乱搞了
...tits up.
没错  疯掉了
Yes, haywire.
-变成了没有上帝的乱世  -天啊
- It all becomes a Godless mess. - Oh, dear.
爱因斯坦讨厌豌豆
Einstein hated peas.
也就是量子论  他说
Quantum Theory, he said,
"上帝不掷骰子"
"God doesn't play dice with the universe."
可是他不仅玩骰子
Seems he not only plays the dice,
还扔到了我们看不到的地方
but he throws them where we can't find them.
上帝又变成了珍稀物种
God is back on the endangered species list.
他应该能适应的
Well, I expect He'll cope.
物理学又登场了
But physics is back in business.
对  物理学又登场了
Yes, physics is back in business.
我以前结过婚
I was married... actually.
可她突然去世了
But suddenly... she passed.
差不多一年了
Almost a year ago now.
白血病
It was leukemia.
她抗争过  我也尽力照顾  可还是...
She fought it and I nursed her, but in the end...
我特别孤独  独守空房
I do get quite lonely... the tyranny of the empty room.
什么的
And all that.
但音乐拯救了我  在唱诗班  教人弹琴
But... music is my salvation... teaching and playing.
算不上职业吧
Not really as a career,
反正我也没有什么野心
but I... I'm not that ambitious, so...
这算不算是罪  我也不知道
Is that a sin? I don't know.
问错人了
Wrong man to ask.
-谢谢你们的招待  -谢谢你能来
- Thank you so much for having me. - Thank you for coming.
真是太...太好了
It was re... really... really wonderful.
如果有什么能帮你的
If there's anything I can do to be of service... to you.
我是说帮你们家
To the family, I mean.
不要客气
I would... consider it a privilege.
我没有孩子  单身也没什么负担
I have no children, or commitments.
我没别的意思  就是想帮你  我...
I only mean that if I... could be of help, I've...
我肯定...  也算是
I'm... really, if I might find a purpose
帮我排解孤独了
that would help alleviate my own situation.
-晚安  -晚安
- Good night. - Night.
我理解你的
I understand...
如果你需要帮助...
If you need help...
并且有人愿意帮忙
If someone is prepared to offer...
我不会反对的
I won't object.
您是一人   也是万物
Calls you one and calls you all,
他的领域  永存于世
to gain his everlasting hall.
生为救赎  解救众生
Christ was born to save. Christ was born to save.
太棒了  大家可以走了
Great! Lovely! Okay! We can go!
-刚刚七点二十五  -谢谢
- Just going on seven twenty-five. - Thank you.
能...谁能给我留一份
I'm... could... could you all leave a copy of that?
我有话要跟你说
There's something I need to tell you.
什么
What?
我怀孕了
I'm pregnant.
天啊  我...我还以为你和斯蒂芬
Gosh! I... I, um... I assumed that you and Stephen...
真...真是太棒了
Well, that's... that's really wonderful.
-确实  -真的  太美妙了
- It is. - Yes, it's wonderful.
-简  恭喜你  -谢谢
- Congratulations, Jane. - Thank you.
说"茄子"  准备好了吗
Everyone say "Cheese"! Ready?
我数到三  1  2  3
Count 3! 1, 2, 3...
茄子
Cheese!
-妈妈  -来了
- Mummy! - Just coming.
那个
Now, you know...
我一直都很支持你
I've always been supportive
不请人来帮忙
of your choice not to have home help,
但我们得想个长远的办法
but we need to find a permanent solution.
这种...这种...
This... this...
这种状况不是长久之计
situation cannot continue,
你得赶紧找个常住的护工
you need to have a proper live-in nurse immediately.
有人照顾我
We have help.
你知道我什么意思
Look... you know what I'm talking about.
我们雇不起护工
We can't afford a live-in nurse.
斯蒂芬  这样不是办法
Stephen, you need to find a way,
为了你的家人
for your family's sake...
你已经是世界名人了
you're world famous.
我是因为黑洞出名的  又不是摇滚乐
For black holes, not for rock concerts.
斯蒂芬  我没开玩笑  这事不能拖
Stephen, this isn't funny, I believe it's urgent.
我们有权知道真相
We do have a right to know.
简  我们有权知道
We have a right to know, Jane.
知道什么
Know what?
蒂莫西的爸爸是谁...
Whose child Timothy is...
斯蒂芬还是乔纳森
Stephen's, or Jonathan's?
我在你们眼里就是那样的人
That's what you think of me?
除了斯蒂芬
There is no way that Timothy
没人可能是蒂莫西的爸爸
could have any other father than Stephen.
行了吧
Enough!
-乔纳森  别走  -我该走了
- Jonathan, please don't go. - I have to go.
-所有人都说我们...  -那又怎样
- Everybody's talking, and... - So, what does it matter?
我很难做下去  我只是想帮你们
It's difficult for me because I'm just trying to help.
我当然知道
I know you're trying to help
而且你帮了很大忙
and your help is valueless.
我想现在我最好还是
The best thing for me right thing right now,
还是...还是
I think, maybe if... if... if...
...退出你们的生活吧
...I just step back for now.
乔纳森  别这样
Please, Jonathan,
我们需要你  孩子需要你
we need you, the children need you,
我需要你  斯蒂芬也需要你
and I need you, and Stephen needs you.
-乔纳森  -别说这些了
- Jonathan... - Don't think of it.
但是  简  还有别的原因
But there's other things as well. Jane, I...
我对你有感觉
I have feelings for you.
我对你也是
And I have feelings for you, too.
简  谢谢你
Thank you, Jane.
有人邀我去波尔多
I've been invited to Bordeaux.
-去哪  -波尔多
- Invited where? - To Bordeaux.
你要去波尔多
To Bordeaux?
马克他们吗
Mark and them?
学生们可以带我去
Students can take me,
我知道你不喜欢坐飞机
I know you hate flying.
我确实讨厌坐飞机
I do hate to fly.
你开车去吧  我们波尔多见
Bring the car, meet me in Bordeaux.
这样孩子们也舒服些
Make the children comfy.
斯蒂芬  你一个人去太不方便了
It'd be too difficult to manage, Stephen.
让乔纳森陪你吧
Bring Jonathan.
他不一定愿意去吧
I doubt he would be willing.
你好啊  斯蒂芬
Hello, Stephen.
-喝这个行吗  -这个...
- Is this okay? - Well...
我是不会说出去的
I won't tell if you won't.
但是...
Just...
别喝多  你还得开车呢
bearing in mind you have to drive.
简需要你的帮助
Jane needs help.
萨拉  千万记得
Sarah, you won't forget to give him
一着陆就给他注射药物
the injection as soon as soon as you land, will you.
到宾馆记得给我打个电话
And you'll call me when you get to the hotel.
-不会忘的  -保证
- I will. -Yes? Promise?
-一定不会  -好
- Yeah. - Good!
斯蒂芬
Stephen?
妈妈带孩子去
Mum'll take the baby.
-她一会就到  -我们波尔多见
- She'll be here any minute. - See you in Bordeaux.
千万注意
You be good.
-他们睡了吗  -睡了
- They asleep? - Yeah.
乔纳森
Jonathan.
Jonathan?
乔纳森  斯蒂芬出事了
Jonathan, it's Stephen, he's been just taken ill,
他突然病重  被送到了医院
he's in the hospital right now,
现在还在昏迷
he's in a coma.
他怎么了
他感染了重度肺炎
现在全靠呼吸机维持
不知道他还能撑多久
我得问问我的同事
能不能撤掉呼吸机
你什么意思
What are you talking about?
可以让他没有痛苦的离开
This way would be a painless end.
让他脱离麻醉状态
If we try to bring him round from the anesthetic
也不一定能保他的命
it's not sure he will survive resuscitation.
让他脱离麻醉状态
You have to bring him round from the anesthetic!
你确定真要这么做
Are you sure it's what you want?
让他呼吸的唯一方法
The only way of weaning him off the ventilator
就是实施气管切开手术
would be to give him a tracheotomy,
在脖子上开刀  从喉咙旁边过去
a hole in the neck, by-passing the throat.
他就再也没法说话了
He will never speak again.
没得商量  必须要保住他的命
There's no question... Stephen must live.
需要什么就用什么
I will see he gets everything he needs.
然后转院回剑桥
I will have him transferred back to Cambridge.
-他很可能下不了手术台  -他能的
- He may not survive the journey. - Yes, he will.
我知道
I know.
我就...
I'll...
不去了
step back.
你东西都带齐了吗
Did you get everything in the car...
他的轮椅  设备什么的
his chair, and his equipment, and everything?
再见了
Goodbye.
斯蒂芬
Stephen?
这是个拼字板
This is a spelling board.
我先说颜色
Firstly, you tell me
你要哪个颜色
what letter you want by blinking
就对我眨下眼睛
when I say the color of the group that contains that letter.
确定了颜色以后
Once I know the group,
我说到你要的字母
you can choose the character inside that group by
你就眨下眼睛
by blinking again when I say the color of each letter with that group...
...很简单
...apparently
我们先试试吧
Let's just try.
绿色
Green.
蓝色
Blue.
粉色
Pink.
黑色
Black.
红色
Red.
斯蒂芬  用哪个颜色的字母
Blink to choose the color of
就对我眨下眼睛好吗
the group of the letter that you want, Stephen.?
绿色
Green.
蓝色
Blue.
粉色
Pink.
黑色
Black.
红色
Red.
-稍等一下  -好的
- Just wait here. - Great.
她来了  很多人推荐她的
She's here, she comes highly recommended.
跟她和气点
Promise not to eat her alive.
好吗
Okay?
来啦
Here we are.
伊莲  这是斯蒂芬
Elaine, Stephen.
斯蒂芬  这是伊莲
Stephen, Elaine.
教授  很高兴见到你
Lovely to meet you, Professor.
你一切都准备好了
Now, you should have everything you need.
还需要什么再找我  我就在隔壁
But if there's anything else, I'll be right next door.
很好  我们可以马上开始了
Great, I think we'll get straight to work.
简  谢谢
Thank you, Jane.
-对了  拜托你关上门  -当然
- Oh, if you just close the doors. - Of course.
那我们就开始了
Let's get started then.
好了
Okay...
红色
Red.
黄色
Yellow.
T
T.
绿色
Green.
黑色  E
Black... "E".
绿色  绿色  A
Green, green, "A".
茶
Tea.
你要一杯茶
You want a cup of tea?
好的
Okay.
要什么口味
Any preference?
我知道你肯定都记住了
You've memorized the board, I know you have.
我没用一天就记住了
I haven't got all day.
绿  绿  绿  黄
Green, green, green, yellow.
黄  B
Yellow, "B".
绿  蓝  黑  粉  红
Green, blue, black, pink, red.
红色吗
Red?
绿  黄  蓝  蓝
Green, yellow, blue, blue.
U 你要加糖和奶  是吗
"U"... should be Builder's Tea, right?
他学的怎么
Well, how did he get on?
他是我遇到过最聪明的人
You know, I think he's the most brilliant man I've ever met.
-你很幸运  -谢谢
- You're very lucky. - Thank you.
连他下面的土地都是伟大的...
You must worship the ground beneath...
他轮椅下面
His wheels.
虽然生病了  他还是很幽默
And he's a perfect patient, he's so funny.
当你了解了他的时候...
When you read about him people...
先看他恢复得什么样
Let's see how he gets on,
好吗  伊莲
shall we, Elaine?
绝对好用
That's quite enough.
你看  它方便调节
As you can see, that it's quite adjustable,
可以变换角度  改变速度
and we can change the angle to whatever speed wants you there.
-这可是尖端科技  -要怎么用
- Ya know, it's cutting-edge. - So, how does it work?
它有一个十分简单的界面
It uses a very simple interface
你可以一个个字母的浏览
that scans through the alphabet
每次选一个字母
and selects each letter one at a time.
用了这个设备  教授大概
I mean, using this technique, the Professor can
每分钟可以写四个单词
expect to write at about four words per minute.
很好啊  总比一分钟一个要好
Good! Better than one a minute.
是啊  而且我从自动答录机里
Yes, and what I've done is taken the components
拿了些零件
from a telephone answering system, actually,
把文字转换成语音
to convert the written text into synthesized speech.
声音是有点像机器人  但总比...
I mean the voice sounds a little bit robotic, but...
我们来试试吧
Shall we give it a try?
-太棒了  -这是按钮
- Great! - Here's the clicker.
右手吗
Right hand?
开始吧
There ya go.
欢迎来到未来世界
Welcome to the future.
我叫斯蒂芬·霍金
My name is Stephen Hawking.
是美国口音的
It's American!
有问题吗
Is that a problem?
这个...有别的选择吗
Oh, my goodness, well... is there another voice?
目前我只有这一种
It's the only one lately I have at the moment.
真棒
I think it's great.
取自歌曲《Daisy Bell》
黛西  黛西  告诉我你的答案  快点
Daisy, Daisy, give me your answer, do.
"说实话  亲爱的  我不在乎"
"Frankly, my dear, I don't give a damn."
《神秘博士》中Dalek的经典台词
消灭
Exterminate!
我要写本书
I will write a book.
关于什么的
About what?
-时间  -时间
- Time. - Time.
时间的本质是什么
What is the nature of time?
时间有没有尽头
Will it ever come to an end?
我们能不能回到过去
Can we go back in time?
也许未来  这些问题会变得
Some day these answers may seem
像地球绕着太阳转一样平常
as obvious to us as the Earth orbiting the sun,
抑或如乌龟塔般荒谬
or perhaps as ridiculous as a tower of tortoises.
古代人对宇宙的认识
唯有时间
Only time,
不管它是什么  才能给我们答案
whatever that may be, will tell.
基普·索恩  致  斯蒂芬·霍金
剑桥大学
教授
Professor?
-是帮我朋友订的  -当然...
- It is for a friend. - Of course it is...
男人都这么说
That's what they all say.
教授  不用在我面前不好意思
You don't have to be embarrassed in front of me, Professor.
我了解你们男人
I know how men are like.
我们来看看吧
Shall we take a look?
来吧
There ya go.
对不起
Oh! I'm Sorry.
下一页
Next one.
怎么了
What?
《时间简史》
我说过  我一直在努力寻找
So I said I had long been looking for
适用于整个宇宙的模型[模特]
a model of the universe.
我终于找到了她
I finally found her.
可不是嘛
I bet you did.
史蒂芬  打扰一下  合同来了
Stephen, I need to steal you, the contracts arrived.
简  能再给我们一小会儿吗
Could you just give us a minute, please, Jane?
好啦
There we go.
焕然一新
Like new.
我们是谁  为何存在于此
Who are we? Why are we here?
这两个问题如果有答案
If ever learn this it would be
会是人类思想史上的重大突破
the ultimate triumph of the human reason,
因为那时  我们才真的理解了上帝
for then we would know the mind of God.
-你真这么觉得  -是的
- Do you mean this? - Yes.
-当然  -所以你相信上帝存在了
- Of course. - So, you're acknowledging Him?
但是
However.
"但是"什么
"However", what?
你不想让我享受一下这一刻吗
Are you actually going to let me have this moment?
不客气
You're welcome.
我请伊莲陪我去美国了
I have asked Elaine to travel with me to America.
她会照顾我的
She will look after me.
是吗
Will she?
是的
Yes.
有人邀你去哪  你都会告诉我的
You always use to tell me when an invitation came in.
又得奖了  我也没办法
Another award, what can you do?
对不起
I'm sorry.
多少年了
How many years?
他们说只有两年
They said two.
已经许多年了
You've had so many.
一切都会好起来的
Everything will be okay.
我爱过你
I have loved you.
我尽力了
I did my best.
小心点
Careful!
-那个留下  -好的
- No, that stays. - All right.
乔纳森  再见
Goodbye, Jonathan.
谢谢
Thank you.
我1963年第一次见到霍金教授
I first met the Professor in 1963.
一转眼  白驹过隙一样
And there you are... time, where did it go?
看着他挑战极限
It has been one of the great joys of my life
无论是科学上的
to watch this man
还是医学上的  都使我倍感欣慰
defy every expectation, both scientific and personal.
有请我敬爱的同事
Please welcome onto the stage my esteemed colleague,
我亲爱的朋友  霍金教授
my dear friend, Professor Hawking.
非常感谢  我们先来讨论
Thank you! Could we please
第一个预选问题  好吗  谢谢
have the first preselected question, thank you.
大家能听到吗
Can you hear me?
现在您已是名扬四海
Now you are recognized everywhere.
您是如何处理大家的关注的呢
How do you deal with all the attention?
最近  我在剑桥被一位游客拦住
I was stopped recently by a tourist at Cambridge
他问我是否真的是霍金
who asked if I was the real Stephen Hawking.
我回答说我不是
I replied I was not,
霍金本人比我帅多了
and said the real one was much better looking.
1979年  您曾表示
In 1979, you talked about
有望在本世纪末
the possibility of a Theory of Everything.
发现适用万物的理论
being discovered before the end of the century.
我现在预言我当时错了
I now predict that I was wrong.
霍金教授  您说过您不信上帝
Professor Hawking, you have said you do not believe in God.
您说过您不信上帝
You have said you did not believe in God.
那么您有什么指导您的生活哲学吗
Do you have a philosophy of life that helps you?
我们人类也不过是高级灵长类动物
It is clear that we are just an advanced breed of primates,
生活在一颗小星球上
on a minor planet orbiting
绕着一颗普通的恒星转
around a very average star,
我们生活的银河系之外
in the outer suburb of one
还有上亿个星系
among a hundred billion galaxies...
然而  自人类文明诞生以来
But, ever since the dawn of civilization,
人们就没有停止过
people have craved for
对世界根本规律的探索
an understanding of the underlying order of the world.
宇宙的边界是什么
There ought to be something
肯定有个特别的答案
very special about the boundary conditions of the universe.
但是还有比没有边界更特别的答案吗
And what can be more special than that there is no boundary?
同样  人类的潜力也不会有边界
And there should be no boundary to human endeavor.
我们都是与众不同的
We are all different.
无论生活多么艰辛
However bad life may seem,
你总会有自己的方式发光
there is always something you can do, and succeed at.
生命不息  希望不止
While there is life, there is hope.
是斯蒂芬的来信
It's from Stephen.
天啊
Gosh.
你眼镜总是这么脏
Your glasses are always dirty.
霍金教授  霍金夫人  女王接见
Professor and Missus Hawking, Her Majesty the Queen.
恭喜你
Congratulations.
我的"荣誉伴侣"
My "Companion of Honor".
干得好  主张自由社会主义的老头子
Not bad for an old liberal socialist.
别担心  你还是可以拒绝授衔的
Don't worry, you can decline the knighthood.
谢谢你请我来
Thank you for today.
真的很棒
It was extraordinary.
我们这一路一直都很棒  是吧
It's all been rather extraordinary, though, hasn't it?
你在写什么
What are you writing?
看看我们的成果
Look what we made.
《时间简史》在全球销量超过千万
虽然已经72岁了  斯蒂芬依然没有退休
继续探索万物理论
他婉拒了女王授予的骑士头衔
简拿到了西班牙诗歌的博士学位
她与乔纳森喜结连理
简和斯蒂芬依然是好朋友  现已经有三个孙辈
英国大学学位分等级
一般来说  一等学位要求均分70以上
霍金的本科三年只有一次考试  也就是毕业考试
由于紧张他发挥失常  成绩处在一等与二等的边缘
因此需要追加一次面试